Finding aid for Abdeen Jabara papers, 1956-1994 0234 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library
Abdeen Jabara papers
1956-1994
1968-1993
Bentley Historical Library
Jabara, Abdeen.
0234 Aa 2
14.4 linear feet
New York attorney originally based in Detroit. Jabara was concerned with issues of civil rights of Arab Americans and the rights of Arabs living or traveling in the United States. He challenged practice of law enforcement agencies to collect information and maintain surveillance of Arabs and Arab Americans. Jabara was involved in the murder trial of Sirhan Sirhan and the extradition case of Ziad Abu Eain. Litigation and case files; subject files regarding his Arab American activism, organizational involvements, and participation in the Middle East delegation of the National Lawyers Guild.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by Abdeen M. Jabara (Donor No. 9120 ) and came to the library in August, 2001. Additions were received in 2007 and in 2012.
Accruals
No further additions to the papers are expected.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to research except for indicated restricted files which require the written permission of the donor for access. These files open with the passing of Mr. Jabara.
Biographical / Historical
Abdeen M. Jabara was born in Mancelona, Michigan in 1940 to Lebanese parents who had immigrated to the United States in the early 20th century, eventually settling in northern Michigan. Jabara took an interest in Middle Eastern affairs throughout his youth and upon graduation from high school in 1958 decided to attend the University of Michigan, largely because the school offered courses in Arabic and had a prominent Arab student population. During his early undergraduate years Jabara determined that in order to learn the Arabic language properly he would have to immerse himself in that culture and so he spent five months living in Cairo, Egypt. He then journeyed by freighter to Lebanon to visit his father's village, where he met his uncle for the first time.
Upon returning from this trip, Jabara's focus centered more on the completion of his undergraduate education at Michigan than on Middle East issues. However, during his years of law school at Wayne State University in Detroit he gradually became more involved with civil rights issues and founded a local chapter of the Civil Rights Research Council. He graduated from law school in 1965 and returned to Lebanon to further develop his Arabic language skills through additional schooling.
Jabara returned to Detroit in 1966 to open his law practice. In 1967, the Arab-Israeli war and the anti-Arab sentiment it created prompted Jabara to become heavily involved with Arab-American issues. Academics of Arab heritage met at the University of Michigan to discuss the political situation and formed the Association of Arab-American University Graduates (AAUG) in 1968. The mission of the AAUG was to promote educational and cultural activities and information about the Arab world and the Arab-American community. Jabara served as the first executive secretary and was later elected president of the group in 1972.
In 1970, Jabara joined the law firm of Lafferty, Reosti, Jabara, Papakhian, Stickgold, James and Smith in Detroit. For the next decade and a half he would fight for the rights of Arabs living or traveling in the United States as well as political activists in general. He did so by challenging the practice of collecting information and maintaining surveillance of Arabs and Arab Americans by such institutions as the Detroit and Michigan State Police, the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and the Secretary of State. Jabara's own case against the FBI, for which he enlisted the help of the ACLU, finally ended in victory in 1984 with the FBI agreeing to destroy his file and acknowledging that collecting the information found within the file violated his constitutional rights.
Throughout his legal career Jabara would take on nationally prominent cases of Arabs and Arab-Americans. Such cases included Sirhan B. Sirhan, convicted in the assassination of Robert F. Kennedy in 1968, and Ziad Abu Eain, wanted for extradition to Israel for a 1979 Palestine Liberation Organization bombing.
Jabara was also involved in the National Lawyer's Guild, an organization founded as an alternative to the more conservative American Bar Association. In 1977 he traveled to Lebanon, Jordan, Israel and the Occupied Territories as part of the NLG's Middle East delegation to report on the condition and treatment of Palestinians living in the Occupied Territories. Jabara became president of the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee in 1986. The ADC, founded by former Senator James Abourezk in 1980, devoted itself to the protection of the rights of people of Arab descent and promoting their cultural heritage. Jabara now (2002) works for the ADC Research Institute in Washington D.C. He recently worked as part of the defense team for Omar Ahmad Ali Abdel Rahman, accused of plotting to blow up New York City landmarks and the 1993 bombing of the World Trade Center. Jabara resides in New York City.
Scope and Contents
The collection has been divided into two series: Litigation/Court Cases and Political and Cultural Activities. The many files of correspondence and press clippings document the types of legal and political battles and causes that Jabara has tackled throughout his career. A limited amount of material in the collection is in Arabic, mostly correspondence and press clippings, and is noted as such in the contents list.
Arab Americans -- Civil rights.; Arab Americans -- Michigan.; Human rights -- Israel.; Human rights -- Palestine.; Israel -- Relations -- Lebanon.; Lawyers -- Michigan.; Lebanon -- Relations -- Israel.; Photographs.; Abu Ayn, Ziyad.; American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee.; B'nai B'rith. Anti-defamation League.; Jabara, Abdeen, 1940-; National Lawyers Guild.; Sirhan, Sirhan Bishara, 1944- -- Trials, litigation, etc.
- Litigation/Court Cases
  Scope and Contents
  The Litigation/Court Cases (5.5 linear feet) series contains seven subseries: Sirhan Defense, Jabara vs. Manufacturer's Bank of Detroit, Jabara vs. Bank of the Commonwealth, Police Surveillance, Jabara vs. FBI, Abu Eain Defense and Miscellaneous Cases. The series consists primarily of court documents, correspondence, press clippings, testimonies, and surveillance files related to his legal cases from the late 1960s to the mid-1980s. It is arranged largely as it was received. Cases with only one folder have been placed in the miscellaneous subseries.
  - Sirhan B. Sirhan Defense
    Heavily documented is the case of Sirhan Bishara Sirhan, the Palestinian immigrant who in 1969 was convicted of the murder of Robert F. Kennedy. Jabara, at age 28, became part of the defense team (with George Shibley and Luke McKissack of Los Angeles) that successfully appealed Sirhan's original death sentence. Jabara advised the original defense team (Grant B. Cooper and Russell Parson, later dismissed by Sirhan) on the political, historical, and cultural aspects of the case. Along with files of court documents, interview transcripts, press clippings, and parole information, this subseries details the failed collaboration agreement between the writer Robert B. Kaiser and Sirhan to produce a book about the case.
    - Sociological/Psychological research literature, 1956-1968 (Box 1)
    - Robert Kaiser Interview, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Interviews with Sirhan family members, circa 1968; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Arguments addressed to the jury, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Investigative Reports and Transcripts, circa 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Jabara's writing about the case, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Press Clippings, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Notes from the case, circa 1969 (Box 1)
    - Elizabeth Young Evans vs. Sirhan, 1969 (Box 1)
    - People of the State of California vs. Sirhan court documents, 1968-1970; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Sirhan vs. Kaiser court documents, 1970; 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Bertrand Russell's statement on Middle East from New York Times, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Parole Petition, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Parole Correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 1)
    - Parole Respondent Statement, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Report of Investigation Board of Prison Terms, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Parole Rescission Consideration, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Psychiatric Evaluation, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Parole Press Clippings, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Speech written by Jabara (?) concerning Middle East, undated (Box 1)
  - Norton F. Dacey, et al v. George Shultz, et al
    The subseries Dacey v. Shultz documents Jabara's role as attorney for the prosecution in the Norton Dacey v. George Shultz case, which challenged national tax-exempt status of the Jewish fundraising organizations United Jewish Appeal and Reconstituted Jewish Agency claiming that these organizations were raising money to fund the political activities of the state of Israel.
    - Clippings, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Clippings (re. Jewish Appeal), 1972 (Box 1)
    - Clippings (re. Reconstituted Jewish Agency), 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - Clippings (re. Reconstituted Jewish Agency), 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Court Documents, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Notes on the Case, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Publication: The Legal Status of Israeli-Zionist Fundraising in the U.S.A.: A Lawsuit by Abdeen Jabara (Box 2)
    - Research-Jewish Agency (Certificate of Incorporation, etc.), 1972 (Box 2)
    - Statement before the House Ways and Means Committee, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Supporting Documents, 1972-1973; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Jabara vs. Manufacturer's National Bank of Detroit
    The Jabara vs. Manufacturer's National Bank of Detroit subseries document Jabara's concern that his activities were being observed and investigated by government agencies. By chance, he learned that Manufacturer's Bank had inquired about accounts held by him at one of its branches. Upon suing the bank, Jabara discovered that this request had been prompted by an FBI inquiry which then led to his suit against the FBI. Materials in these files include court documents and Jabara's correspondence with bank management.
    - Court Documents, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Bank Disclosure Litigation Examples, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Jabara vs. Bank of Commonwealth
    - Miscellaneous, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - Court Documents, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Police Surveillance (Benkert et al. vs. Michigan State Police)
    Soon after Jabara's cases against the banks, he joined a class action suit (Benkert vs. Michigan State Police) against the Michigan State police that accused them of illegally and unconstitutionally collecting information on various political activists. Court documents, correspondence, press clippings and photocopies of Jabara's Detroit police files are contained in the Police Surveillance subseries.
    - Court Documents, 1975-1981 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Press Clippings, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Jabara's Detroit Police File,1968-1975, 4 folders (Box 2)
      Conditions Governing Access
      restricted; requires written permission of the donor
  - Jabara vs. Federal Bureau of Investigations (FBI)
    The Jabara vs. FBI subseries consists mainly of court documents stemming from the lengthy trial that spanned the administration of several FBI directors including L. Patrick Gray, Clarence M. Kelley, and William H. Webster. In the various suits, Jabara contended that his civil rights were violated as the FBI monitored his activities through wiretapping and surveillance. The files also contain a large amount of correspondence including that between Jabara and John H.F. Shattuck, his ACLU lawyer. Jabara eventually won his case against the FBI in 1984.
    - Background Information, 1971-1982; 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1986; 15 folders (Box 3)
    - Jabara's FBI File, 1968-1975; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Press Clippings, 1974-1983 (Box 3)
    - Case No. 39065 Jabara vs. Directors' L. Patrick Gray, Clarence M. Kelley, William H. Webster
      - Bank Disclosure Legislation (H.B. 5237), 1975-1976 (Box 3)
      - Court Documents, 1972-1983; 15 folders (Box 3)
      - Court Documents, 1972-1983; 10 folders (Box 4)
    - Case No. 80-1391 Jabara vs. William H. Webster et al.,1980-1981, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Case No. 82-1682 Jabara vs. William H. Webster et al. (Supreme Court Case), 1982-1983 (Box 4)
  - James Lafferty, et al v. William Rogers et al
    The Lafferty v. Rogers case is a Freedom of Information Act suit where the prosecutor sued for the right to access documents relating to the United States government's political and military involvement in the Middle East.
    - Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
    - Court Documents, 1971; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Research, 1970-1971; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Palestine Congress of North America v. Alexander Haig
    In Palestine Congress of North American v. Alexander Haig, Jabara represented a group of US citizens who, being landholders in Lebanon, sued the Secretary of State Alexander Haig claiming that through providing arms to Israel the US government was providing for damage to their property in Lebanon.
    - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - Court Documents, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Notes and Retainer Agreements, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Research and Press Clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - State of Israel v. Sami Esmail (Sami Esmail Defense)
    Jabara acted as a legal advisor in the defense of Sami Esmail in the State of Israel v. Sami Esmail, an Israeli court case. Sami Esmail, a Palestinian citizen and legal resident of the United States was imprisoned in Israel for alleged involvement in the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, considered a terrorist organization by the state of Israel. This subseries contains clippings and correspondence relating to Esmail's trial and subsequent imprisonment, as well as unofficial transcripts of the court proceedings.
    - Clippings, 1977-1979; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (FOIA Requests), 1978 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Political Action), 1978 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Court Documents (Affidavits), 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Israeli Court Transcripts, unofficial, 1978; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Notes, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Sworn Statements, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Ziad (Ziyad) Abu Eain Defense
    - Human Rights Report, Department of State, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Sami Esmail Information, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Grand Jury Investigation, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Mufida Jabar Confession, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Jamel Yassin Confession and Trial Transcripts, 1979; 1980 (Box 5)
    - Prison and Medical Reports (Abu Eain), 1979-1980 (Box 5)
    - Jerome Radick Information, Court Documents, 1979-1982 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence
      - 1979-1982, 1984; 7 folders (Box 6)
      - Arabic, circa 1980 (Box 6)
    - Court Documents
      - Case No. 79 M 175 (Extradition of Ziad Abu Eain), 1979; 10 folders (Box 6)
      - Case No. 79 C 5477 (Abu Eain vs. Peter Wilkes, U.S. Marshall for the Northern District of Illinois, in U.S. District Court), 1979-1980; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Case No. 80-1487 (Abu Eain vs. Peter Wilkes in U.S. Court of Appeals), 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous, 1979-1981 (Box 6)
    - Defense Exhibits (Box 6)
    - Department of State File (Abu Eain), 1979-1981; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Receipts and Accounts, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
    - Support for Abu Eain, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
    - Abu Eain Defense Committee, circa 1981 (Box 7)
    - American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC), 1981 (Box 7)
    - Mary Brightwell Edwards paper, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Buchwald Ruling on Extradition of Desmond Mackin, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Desmond Mackin Extradition Case Court Documents, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Reports on Mistreatment of Arab Prisoners by Israel, circa 1981 (Box 7)
    - Extradition Act of 1981 (S. 1639) (Box 7)
    - Petition to Deny Extradition, circa 1981 (Box 7)
    - Extradition Information, 1982; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Extradition Legislation, 1981-1983; 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Political Offense Exception and the Rule of Non-inquiry Extradition paper, circa 1982 (Box 7)
    - Extradition, Political Offenses, and the U.S.-U.K. Treaty, 1985 (Box 7)
    - Jabara vs. Secretary of State (Alexander Haig and George P. Schultz)
      General
      a Freedom of Information (FOIA) case wherein Jabara sued the Secretary of State for access to documents relating the Ziad defense
      - Correspondence, 1978-1985; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Court Documents (Case No. 81-71421), 1981-1984; 11 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1985; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Notes, circa 1981-1982 (Box 8)
    - Photographs (Abu Eain and Pro-Palestinian March), undated (Box 9)
    - Press Clippings, 1979-1984; 7 folders (Box 9)
      one folder is in Arabic
    - Research, 7th Circuit Judges, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Research, General, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Supporting Documents (in Hebrew) (Box 9)
    - Transcript of Proceedings (partial), 1979 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Cases
    - F.R.E.E.D.O.M. v. Henry Kissinger, 1975 (Box 9)
    - Harassment of Dr. Seif El-Wady Ramahi, 1973-1975 (Box 9)
    - Khalil and Yousef Odah v. State of Israel, 1975; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - National Lawyers Guild vs. Attorney General et al., 1979 (Box 9)
    - Nagi Mohamed vs. Chrysler Corporation, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Katherine Amen vs. City of Dearborn, 1983 (Box 9)
    - James Akins et. al. vs. Federal Elections Committee, 1989-1992 (Box 9)
  - Anti-defamation League (ADL) of B'nai B'rith
    The Anti-Defamation League of B'nai Brith subseries is dedicated to case that took place in San Francisco, Calif. Anti-Defamation League (ADL), formerly known as Anti-Defamation League of B'nai Brith, is an organization that, among other tasks, monitors activities of extremist organizations and hate groups. The 1993 case involved a San Francisco area antique dealer Roy Bullock, who served as ADL's investigator, and San Francisco police Inspector and former CIA agent Tom Gerard. Bullock and Gerard gathered and forwarded information about individuals and organizations to ADL. Investigation revealed that through Bullock and Gerard, ADL has compiled files on thousands of individuals and hundreds of groups across the political spectrum; among them prevailed Arab and Palestinian individuals and organizations, but also such organizations as NAACP, ACLU, labor unions, ACT-UP, Mother Jones magazine, Jews for Jesus, among others. Jabara was member of the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC) legal team working on a lawsuit against ADL. Material in the subseries is mostly dated 1993, unless specified otherwise, and includes legal research and background materials, court documents (pleadings, summaries) and their drafts, correspondence and memoranda, material about related cases, press releases, and unsorted newspaper articles and clippings.
    - ADL Defense (Box 14)
    - ADL history and background material, 1978-1993 (Box 14)
    - Articles and reports, 1983-1994 (Box 14)
      by Jabara and others
    - Civil Disturbance Police Guidelines (Box 14)
    - Coalition Against Surveillance (Box 14)
    - Correspondence and memoranda
      - 1976, 1986-1987 (Box 14)
        related to case
      - January-June 1993 (Box 14)
      - July 1993-February1994 (Box 14)
    - Court documents
      - Affidavits and Exhibits (Box 14)
      - Complaints (Box 14)
      - Declaration of Albert Mokhiber, July 1993 (Box 14)
      - Discovery (Box 14)
      - Motion for Protective Order (ADL), October 1993 (Box 14)
      - Motion to Discover (Tom Gerard), September 1993 (Box 14)
      - Search Warrant (Tom Gerard), 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Summaries (Box 14)
    - Los Angeles Board of Civil Service hearings, 1992 (Box 14)
    - Pasadena, California, 1992 (Box 14)
      Vicky Tamoush
    - Portland, Oregon ADL (Box 14)
    - Press releases (Box 14)
    - Research, legal
      - Congressional hearings, 1948 (Box 14)
      - ACLU vs. City of Chicago, 1975 (Box 14)
      - Correspondence and memoranda (Box 14)
      - Drafts of court documents (Box 14)
      - Irwin Suall (Box 14)
      - Other cases against ADL (Box 14)
        inquiry by another firm
    - San Francisco Arab American community (Box 14)
    - San Francisco Police Commission (Box 14)
    - Newspaper articles and clippings, 1993 (Box 15)
      unsorted
- Political and Cultural Activities
  The Political and Cultural Activities (3.5 linear feet) series contains information about the Jabara's cultural and political activities interests. The series has been arranged alphabetically. Perhaps the most extensive portion of the series is the documentation of the 1977 National Lawyers Guild Middle East Delegation that traveled to Lebanon, Jordan, Israel and the Occupied Territories in July 1977 to observe and report on the Palestine liberation movement, the state of opposition in Israel, and the condition and treatment of Palestinians living in Israeli Occupied Territories. Jabara was influential in arranging the trip and was also a member of the delegation. Included in this collection are several folders of correspondence, clippings that express the attitude towards the visit from the popular and legal press, and copies of the minority and majority reports compiled and published by the NLG.
  Additional areas of strength in this series include press clippings and information about the Arab-American community in the Detroit Metropolitan area, documentation through papers and journals of the human rights abuses of Palestinians living in occupied Israeli territory, refuge camps, and prisons, and documentation of the harassment of Arab-Americans through testimonials and correspondence with Jabara. Materials of interest relating to "Operation Boulder" include correspondence and press clippings. Operation Boulder was a collaborative campaign initiated by President Nixon and included the FBI, CIA, Immigration and Naturalization Service, and the Department of Transportation. It began in September 1972 after 11 Israeli athletes were murdered at the Olympic games in Munich. The campaign called for the intensive investigation and screening of the activity of Arabs in the United States with the aim of eliminating possible terrorist acts against Israeli citizens. The series also contains extensive information about Jabara's native land of Lebanon, including correspondence and press clippings about the civil war in the mid-1970s and the treatment of Lebanese prisoners taken during the Israeli invasion of Lebanon in 1982.
  - AAUG (Association of Arab-American University Graduates), 1968-1976; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - ACD (American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee), 1980-1981 (Box 9)
  - Ariel Sharon vs. Time, Inc., 1983-1984 (Box 9)
  - Black/Arab Coalition, 1979-1983 (Box 9)
  - Detroit Arab-American Community
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1979 (Box 9)
    - Press Clippings, 1976-1985 (Box 9)
    - Mounted Certificates for Palestine Day and Week, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Foreign Affairs Committee, Testimony (Box 10)
  - Harassment of Arab-Americans
    - Correspondence
      - 1972-1979 (Box 10)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 10)
    - Khaled Amghames File, 1970-1972 (Box 10)
    - William Biggin vs. INS (Immigration and Naturalization Service), 1972 (Box 10)
    - Press Clippings, 1972-1978 (Box 10)
    - Testimonials and Miscellaneous, circa 1972-1974 (Box 10)
  - Hunt Oil Investigation, 1973-1975 (Box 10)
  - Imprisoned Members of the Iranian Socialist Workers Party (Box 10)
  - Israel Aliyah Center Literature, 1969-1971 (Box 10)
  - Israeli Human Rights Abuses (Publications and Literature), 1968-1975; 18 folders (Box 10)